<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Applied Data Science &amp; Artificial Intelligence</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/</link><description>Recent content on Applied Data Science &amp; Artificial Intelligence</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 17:14:54 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://adsai.inginf.units.it/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Arianna Tasciotti</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/arianna-tasciotti/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 17:14:54 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/arianna-tasciotti/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Luigi Rovito</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/luigi-rovito/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 17:13:24 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/luigi-rovito/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Giorgia Nadizar</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/giorgia-nadizar/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 17:12:11 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/giorgia-nadizar/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Emanuele Gosamo</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/emanuele-gosamo/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 17:11:05 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/emanuele-gosamo/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Luis Gerardo Leon-Vega</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/luis-gerardo-leon-vega/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 17:09:39 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/luis-gerardo-leon-vega/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Federico Julian Camerota Verdù</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/federico-julian-camerota-verdu/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 17:05:19 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/federico-julian-camerota-verdu/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Lorenzo Basile</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/lorenzo-basile/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 17:05:01 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/lorenzo-basile/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Alessio Ansuini</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/alessio-ansuini/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:49:44 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/alessio-ansuini/</guid><description>Dr Ansuini graduated in Physics from Sapienza University of Rome and obtained a PhD in Physics in the same University (2010). He worked in SISSA as a postdoc in several groups (Neurobiology and Cognitive Neuroscience sector) on the analysis of experimental data with machine learning and deep learning models. Since 2019 he works in Area Science Park as a Research Technologist and since 2020 he teaches the course of Deep Learning in the Master in Data Science and Scientific Computing (DSSC).</description></item><item><title>Alexandro Saro</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/alexandro-saro/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:49:36 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/alexandro-saro/</guid><description>Alex Saro graduated in Physics from the University of Trieste (2003 and 2006), and obtained a PhD in Physics from the University of Trieste (2009). He worked as a Senior Research Scientist at Ludwig Maximilian of Munich from 2010 and 2017, where he moved as Ricercatore di II livello (equivalent of associate professor) at INAF - Trieste. Since 2021, he is an associate professor of the Physics Department of the University of Trieste.</description></item><item><title>Stefano Cozzini</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/stefano-cozzini/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:49:24 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/stefano-cozzini/</guid><description>Dr. Cozzini is presently the director of the Institute of Research and Technology (RET) at Area Science Park where he is managing all the scientific infrastructures of the campus, including a NGS platform and the ORFEO HPC/AI data center. He teaches HPC topics at DSSC and MHPC and is currently involved in several National and European projects on the above topic. His present scientific interest are in the area between HPC and AI and on FAIR data management.</description></item><item><title>Antonio Celani</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/antonio-celani/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:49:16 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/antonio-celani/</guid><description>Antonio Celani earned his PhD at Politecnico di Torino, Italy in 1998. After post-doctoral fellowships at Max Planck Institute in Munich and at the Observatoire de la Côte d&amp;rsquo;Azur he became researcher for the French National Research Council (CNRS) in 2000. In 2007 he joined the Institut Pasteur Paris as a research director where he started working at the interface between physics and biology. Since 2014 he also is research scientist at The Abdus Salam International Center for Theoretical Physics - ICTP where he works on subjects at the crossroads between physics, biology, and artificial intelligence.</description></item><item><title>Andrea De Lorenzo</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/andrea-de-lorenzo/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:40:35 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/andrea-de-lorenzo/</guid><description>Andrea De Lorenzo is assistant professor at the University of Trieste. His research interests include evolutionary computation, application of machine learning techniques to engineering, computer security problems, information extraction and natural language processing.
He won the silver medal at the 13th Human-Competitive Awards, 2016, for Human-Competitive Results produced by Genetic and Evolutionary Computation. He serves as reviewers for many international journals closely related to his research interests; he is a member of the scientific/program committee of the most important conferences on evolutionary computation.</description></item><item><title>Francesco Pauli</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/francesco-pauli/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:37:44 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/francesco-pauli/</guid><description>Felice Andrea Pellegrino is Associate Professor of Automatica at the Department of Engineering and Architecture, University of Trieste, where he teaches Control Theory and Computer Vision. He has been Research Fellow at SISSA and University of Udine. He is Associate Editor of the IEEE Control Systems Letters and member of the Conference Editorial Boards of the IEEE Control Systems Society and of the European Control Association. His research interests include Control Theory, Machine Learning and Computer Vision.</description></item><item><title>Alberto D'Onofrio</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/alberto-d-onofrio/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:35:52 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/alberto-d-onofrio/</guid><description>Dr d’Onofrio works at the interface between Informatics, Physics and Applied Mathematics. He graduated in Electrical Engineering at Pisa University (1993), and got a PhD in ‘Medical Computer Sciences’ at the Roma Sapienza University (2000). He has been PostDoc, Researcher (2003) and Group Leader (2008) at the European Institute of Oncology, Milan. Between 2014 and 2020 he was Directeur de Recherche at the International Prevention Research Institute, Lyon. Since 2022 he is a Senior Researcher in Computer Science at the Trieste University.</description></item><item><title>Eric Medvet</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/eric-medvet/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:25:31 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/eric-medvet/</guid><description>Eric Medvet is an Associate Professor in Computer Engineering at the Department of Engineering and Architecture of University of Trieste, Italy. He founded and leads the Evolutionary Robotics and Artificial Life lab (ERALlab); he is the co-founder and co-head of the Machine Learning Lab. His research activities include evolutionary computation, artificial life, embodied intelligence, and machine learning applications. He is a member of the program committee of the most important conferences on evolutionary computation.</description></item><item><title>Sara Marceglia</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/sara-marceglia/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:25:24 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/sara-marceglia/</guid><description>Sara Marceglia is Professor of eHealth at the University of Trieste. Her research interests regard the development of personalized applications, decision support systems, and telemedicine systems for fragile patients, with particular attention to neurologic patients. She works to implement integrated systems for chronic patients’ management, including cloud-based data collection platforms, big data analytics infrastructures, ecosystems of personalized app for Patient Reported Outcome collection, and wearable non-stigmatizing telemonitoring devices. She graduated in Biomedical Engineering at (2004) and got her PhD in Bioengineering (2009) at the Politecnico di Milano.</description></item><item><title>Luca Manzoni</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/luca-manzoni/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:23:12 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/luca-manzoni/</guid><description>Luca Manzoni is an assistant professor (associate professor from July 2022) in the field of Evolutionary Computation, Artificial Intelligence, and Natural Computing. He received multiple awards for his research work, he is currently an associate editor of Swarm and Evolutionary Computation. In the last five years he held courses from the bachelor to the PhD level on the topics of algorithms, computational complexity, computer architectures, operating systems, information retrieval, and evolutionary computation.</description></item><item><title>Leonardo Egidi</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/leonardo-egidi/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:22:02 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/leonardo-egidi/</guid><description>Dr Egidi graduated in Statistics from the University of Trieste (2011 and 2014), and obtained a PhD in Statistics from the University of Padova (2018). Since 2020 he is an Assistant Professor of Statistics at the University of Trieste. He regularly teaches Bayesian inference and statistical methods, and is interested in computational statistics and its applications to biostatistics, social sciences and sport analytics. Dr Egidi is a fellow of the Italian Statistical Society and the International Society for Bayesian Analysis.</description></item><item><title>Domenico De Stefano</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/domenico-de-stefano/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:15:59 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/domenico-de-stefano/</guid><description>Domenico De Stefano obtained his PhD in Statistics from the University of Naples Federico II in 2009. Since 2020, he is Full Professor of Social Statistics at the University of Trieste. His teaching activities are in the field of statistics, survey methods and network analysis. His research interests mainly focus on social network analysis and statistical modelling, with particular attention to the development of new methodological tools to explore relational data.</description></item><item><title>Daniele Coslovich</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/daniele-coslovich/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:14:27 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/daniele-coslovich/</guid><description>Prof. Coslovich is Associate Professor at the Physics Department of the University of Trieste since 2020. Previously, he worked at the University of Montpellier and at the Technical University of Vienna. His research interests focus on the theoretical and computational modelling of disordered systems and soft materials. He also contributes to several open source packages for molecular simulations and data analysis.</description></item><item><title>Lorenzo Castelli</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/lorenzo-castelli/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:12:43 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/lorenzo-castelli/</guid><description>Prof. Lorenzo Castelli graduated in Electronic Engineering (1997) from the University of Trieste and holds a PhD in Transportation (2002) from the same university. Since 2019 he’s associate professor in Operations Research. His research activity focusses on productivity analysis and mathematical optimisation applied to logistics and transport, with emphasis on various aspects of air traffic management, including market-based mechanisms for slot allocation and pricing mechanisms to redistribute traffic across the European air network.</description></item><item><title>Luca Bortolussi</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/luca-bortolussi/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 15:47:43 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/luca-bortolussi/</guid><description>Luca Bortolussi is full professor of computer science at the University of Trieste. He obtained a phd in computer science from the university of Udine in 2007, and after that worked in Trieste, with periods spent in the School of Informatics of the University of Edinburgh and in the Faculty of Informatics of Saarland University in Saarbruecken. His research interests cover machine learning and artificial intelligence, including explainable AI integrating symbolic and statistic methods, robust machine learning, data generation, stochastic simulation, control and reinforcement learning, with application to complex systems, cyber-physical systems and medicine.</description></item><item><title>Giulia Bernardini</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/giulia-bernardini/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 15:46:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/giulia-bernardini/</guid><description>Dr. Bernardini received her M.Sc. in Mathematics from the University of Pisa in 2017, and obtained a Ph.D. in Computer Science from the University of Milano-Bicocca in 2021, winning the Best Italian Ph.D. Thesis in Theoretical Computer Science prize, awarded by the Italian Chapter of EATCS. She spent one year as a Postdoc researcher at the Centrum Wiskunde en Informatica in Amsterdam, and she is an Assistant Professor at the University of Trieste since January 2022.</description></item><item><title>Marco Barchiesi</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/marco-barchiesi/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 15:44:53 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/marco-barchiesi/</guid><description>Since October 2019, I am associate professor of probability at the Department of Mathematics and Geosciences of the University of Trieste. I spent most of my career, from October 2010 to September 2019, at the University of Naples Federico II, first as ERC postdoc, then as assistant professor, and finally as associate professor in mathematical analysis. Before that, I was postdoc at the Basque Center for Applied Mathematics and at the Center for Nonlinear Analysis, Carnegie Mellon University.</description></item><item><title>Giovanni Baj</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/giovanni-baj/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 19:02:41 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/giovanni-baj/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Sylvio Barbon Jr</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/sylvio-barbon-jr/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 19:02:13 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/sylvio-barbon-jr/</guid><description>Sylvio is an Associate Professor at the Department of Engineering and Architecture at the University of Trieste (UNITS) and part of the Machine Learning Lab. Previously, he was the leader of the research group that studies machine learning at the State University of Londrina (UEL), Brazil. He received his BSc degree in Computer Science in 2005, MSc degree in Computational Physics from the University of São Paulo (2007), a degree in Computational Engineering in 2008, and PhD degree (2011) from IFSC/USP.</description></item><item><title>Giulia Barbati</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/giulia-barbati/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 18:59:47 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/giulia-barbati/</guid><description>G. Barbati graduated in Statistics from University of Rome (1999) and obtained a PhD in Functional Neuroimaging from University of Chieti-Pescara (2007). Since 2019, she is Associate Professor in Medical Statistics at University of Trieste. She works on survival analysis methods and joint models for longitudinal and time-to-event data. Moreover, she is interested in statistical methods for exploiting informational content of health administrative data and in machine learning (ML) algorithms for risk prediction.</description></item><item><title>Alice Antonello</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/alice-antonello/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 15:26:42 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/alice-antonello/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Simone Arnaldi</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/simone-arnaldi/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 14:45:44 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/simone-arnaldi/</guid><description>Simone Arnaldi graduated in International relations and diplomacy (2000) from the University of Trieste, and obtained a PhD from the Pontifical Gregorian University (2005). He is Associate Professor of Sociology at the University of Trieste. He studies the governance of science, technology, and innovation (STI) governance, with a focus on responsibility in STI and on science diplomacy. He is the President of the Italian Society of Science and Technology Studies (STS Italia).</description></item><item><title>Giulio Caravagna</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/giulio-caravagna/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 15:44:26 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/giulio-caravagna/</guid><description>Since 2020, Giulio leads the Cancer Data Science Laboratory at the University of Trieste, a group of interdisciplinary scientists working at the intersection of computational and experimental research, approaching real-world biological questions with state-of-the-art Machine Learning. Giulio trained in computer science at the University of Pisa; after a PhD (2011), he carried out postdoctoral training in mathematical models for biology at Milan-Bicocca, in machine learning for biology at the University of Edinburgh , and in evolutionary cancer genomics at the Institute of Cancer Research.</description></item><item><title>Courses</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/</guid><description>Courses offered by the PhD program )" Teacher(s) CFU Hours Period Review of statistical modelling and inference Egidi, Pauli, Torelli 3 20+4 april-may Advanced topics in statistical modeling Egidi, Pauli, Torelli 3 18+6 may-june Population Based Optimisation Methods Manzoni 2 16 jan-feb Biodiversity informatics Martellos 2 18 june-september Advanced topics in Reinforcement Learning Celani 1 10 May Advanced topics in network analysis: theory and applications De Stefano 1,5 12 september Evolutionary Robotics Medvet 1,5 12 jan-feb Optimization-based control Pellegrino 1,5 12 september/october Statistical methods for clinical prediction models and causal inference Barbati 1 6 june Copula modeling – Extreme value theory Pappadà, Pauli 2 16 june-july Artificial Intelligence in society Arnaldi 1 10 september Law and AI Infantino 2,5 20 spring Explainable AI Bortolussi + guests 1,5 12 june-july Courses offered by the SISSA PhD program (see https://datascience.</description></item><item><title>Courses</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/curricula/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/curricula/</guid><description>The ADSAI PhD program is divided into 3 main curricula:
Industry 4.0, smart cities, transportation and natural sciences; Life sciences and medicine; Economy and society. Refer to the ADSAI faculty page to discover the research interests of the members of each curriculum.
Industry 4.0, smart cities, transportation and natural sciences This curriculum
Members Coordinator: Prof Luca Bortolussi.
Prof Luca Bortolussi (lbortolussi@units.it), Department of Mathematics and Geosciences Prof Marco Barchiesi (mbarchiesi@units.</description></item><item><title>F.A.Q.</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/faq/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/faq/</guid><description>Frequently Asked Questions Is your teaching in English?
Yes, all of our teaching is in English.
How does the application process work?
Please see the How to Apply page for details.
What about funding?
Students are ranked and, every year, a number of fellowships that cover PhD fees and provide extra salary (around XXXXX €/yr net) are usually available. The number of fellowships might change on a yearly basis, and this type of fellowships are free from a project (i.</description></item><item><title>Faculty</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/_faculty/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/_faculty/</guid><description>ADSAI Program Director Prof. Francesco Pauli, Department of Economics, Business, Mathematics and Statistics (DEAMS), University of Trieste.
Contacts: dottorato.adsai@units.it.
ADSAI core members Core members are potential supervisors for ADSAI PhD students, are involved in teaching and training and are responsible for the governance of the ADSAI PhD program.
University of Trieste faculties Email Brief biography Research Interests Laboratory Simone Arnaldi sarnaldi@units.it Simone Arnaldi graduated in International relations and diplomacy (2000) from the University of Trieste, and obtained a PhD from the Pontifical Gregorian University (2005).</description></item><item><title>HOW TO APPLY</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/how-to-apply/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/how-to-apply/</guid><description>Admission Procedure To be done</description></item><item><title>MISSION</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/mission/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/mission/</guid><description>Mission Across all fields, technological development is fostering the collection of large amounts of complex datasets that require advanced data science skills to be organised, processed and successfully mined. Without novel machine learning methods able to interpret and extract knowledge from those datasets, our capacity to understand the world is severely limited. Data Science and Artificial Intelligence are two cross-disciplinary fields rooted at the grounds of computer science, mathematics, statistics and physics to advance our ability to understand complex phenomena through the use of massive data.</description></item><item><title>People</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/_people/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/_people/</guid><description/></item><item><title>PhD PROGRAM</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/phd-program/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/phd-program/</guid><description>Why a PhD in applied Data Science and Artificial Intelligence? The aim of this new PhD programme at UNITS is to provide students with the modern tools of Data Science and Artificial Intelligence, preparing them to create new data analysis methods and giving them the expertise to apply cutting-edge tools to problems in the real world. Our research spans from theoretical to applied aspects of data science and machine learning, aiming at understanding how modern methodologies became popular, framing their limitations and highlighting their possibility of extension.</description></item><item><title>Students</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/_students/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/_students/</guid><description>2021 Cohort Student Email Bachelor of Science Master of Science ADSAI supervisor(s) External supervisors Topic Alice Antonello alice.antonello@phd.units.it Biotechnology (University of Turin) Quantitative and Computational Biology (University of Trento) Giulio Caravagna Computational methods for tumor evolution Giovanni Baj giovanni.baj@phd.units.it Physics (University of Insubria) Physics (University of Insubria) Giulia Barbati Arjuna Scagnetto (ASUGI) Applications of AI in Health Care Lorenzo Basile lorenzo.</description></item></channel></rss>