<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Applied Data Science &amp; Artificial Intelligence</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/</link><description>Recent content on Applied Data Science &amp; Artificial Intelligence</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://adsai.units.it/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Courses</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/courses/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.units.it/courses/</guid><description>Courses offered by the PhD program )" Teacher(s) CFU Hours Period Review of statistical modelling and inference Egidi 3 20+4 Advanced topics in statistical modeling Egidi, Pauli, Torelli 3 18+6 jan-feb Population Based Optimisation Methods Manzoni 2 16 jan-feb Biodiversity informatics Martellos 2 18 jan-feb or jul-aug Advanced topics in statistical modeling Celani 1 10 spring Advanced topics in network analysis: theory and applications De Stefano 1,5 12 Evolutionary Robotics Medvet 1,5 12 jan-feb Statistical methods for clinical prediction models Barbati 1 6 feb Copula modeling – Extreme value theory Pappadà, Pauli 2 16 jan-feb Artificial Intelligence in society Arnaldi 1 10 Law and AI Infantino+guests 2,5 20 spring Explainable AI Bortolussi + guests 1,5 12 may-jul Courses offered by the SISSA PhD program (see https://datascience.</description></item><item><title>Courses</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/curricula/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.units.it/curricula/</guid><description>The ADSAI PhD program is divided into 3 main curricula:
Industry 4.0, smart cities, transportation and natural sciences; Life sciences and medicine; Economy and society. Refer to the ADSAI faculty page to discover the research interests of the members of each curriculum.
Industry 4.0, smart cities, transportation and natural sciences This curriculum
Members Coordinator: Prof Luca Bortolussi.
Prof Luca Bortolussi (lbortolussi@units.it), Department of Mathematics and Geosciences Prof Marco Barchiesi (mbarchiesi@units.</description></item><item><title>F.A.Q.</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/faq/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.units.it/faq/</guid><description>Frequently Asked Questions Is your teaching in English?
Yes, all of our teaching is in English.
How does the application process work?
Please see the How to Apply page for details.
What about funding?
Students are ranked and, every year, a number of fellowships that cover PhD fees and provide extra salary (around XXXXX €/yr net) are usually available. The number of fellowships might change on a yearly basis, and this type of fellowships are free from a project (i.</description></item><item><title>Faculty</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/faculty/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.units.it/faculty/</guid><description>ADSAI Program Director Prof. Francesco Pauli, Department of Economics, Business, Mathematics and Statistics (DEAMS), University of Trieste.
Contacts: dottorato.adsai@units.it.
ADSAI core members Email Brief biography Research Interests Laboratory Simone Arnaldi sarnaldi@units.it Simone Arnaldi graduated in International relations and diplomacy (2000) from the University of Trieste, and obtained a PhD from the Pontifical Gregorian University (2005). He is Associate Professor of Sociology at the University of Trieste.</description></item><item><title>HOW TO APPLY</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/how-to-apply/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.units.it/how-to-apply/</guid><description>Admission Procedure To be done</description></item><item><title>People</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/people/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.units.it/people/</guid><description/></item><item><title>PhD PROGRAM</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/phd-program/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.units.it/phd-program/</guid><description>Why a PhD in applied Data Science and Artificial Intelligence? The aim of this new PhD programme at UNITS is to provide students with the modern tools of Data Science and Artificial Intelligence, preparing them to create new data analysis methods and giving them the expertise to apply cutting-edge tools to problems in the real world. Our research spans from theoretical to applied aspects of data science and machine learning, aiming at understanding how modern methodologies became popular, framing their limitations and highlighting their possibility of extension.</description></item><item><title>Students</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/students/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.units.it/students/</guid><description>2021 Cohort Student Email Bachelor of Science Master of Science ADSAI supervisor(s) External supervisors Topic Alice Antonello alice.antonello@phd.units.it Biotechnology (University of Turin) Quantitative and Computational Biology (University of Trento) Giulio Caravagna Computational methods for tumor evolution Giovanni Baj giovanni.baj@phd.units.it Physics (University of Insubria) Physics (University of Insubria) Giulia Barbati Arjuna Scagnetto (ASUGI) Applications of AI in Health Care Lorenzo Basile lorenzo.</description></item></channel></rss>