<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Applied Data Science &amp; Artificial Intelligence</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/</link><description>Recent content on Applied Data Science &amp; Artificial Intelligence</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 17:14:54 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://adsai.inginf.units.it/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Arianna Tasciotti</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/arianna-tasciotti/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 17:14:54 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/arianna-tasciotti/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Luigi Rovito</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/luigi-rovito/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 17:13:24 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/luigi-rovito/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Giorgia Nadizar</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/giorgia-nadizar/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 17:12:11 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/giorgia-nadizar/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Emanuele Gosamo</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/emanuele-gosamo/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 17:11:05 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/emanuele-gosamo/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Luis Gerardo Leon-Vega</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/luis-gerardo-leon-vega/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 17:09:39 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/luis-gerardo-leon-vega/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Federico Julian Camerota Verdù</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/federico-julian-camerota-verdu/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 17:05:19 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/federico-julian-camerota-verdu/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Lorenzo Basile</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/lorenzo-basile/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 17:05:01 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/lorenzo-basile/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Alessio Ansuini</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/alessio-ansuini/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:49:44 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/alessio-ansuini/</guid><description>Dr Ansuini graduated in Physics from Sapienza University of Rome and obtained a PhD in Physics in the same University (2010). He worked in SISSA as a postdoc in several groups (Neurobiology and Cognitive Neuroscience sector) on the analysis of experimental data with machine learning and deep learning models. Since 2019 he works in Area Science Park as a Research Technologist and since 2020 he teaches the course of Deep Learning in the Master in Data Science and Scientific Computing (DSSC).</description></item><item><title>Alexandro Saro</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/alexandro-saro/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:49:36 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/alexandro-saro/</guid><description>Alex Saro graduated in Physics from the University of Trieste (2003 and 2006), and obtained a PhD in Physics from the University of Trieste (2009). He worked as a Senior Research Scientist at Ludwig Maximilian of Munich from 2010 and 2017, where he moved as Ricercatore di II livello (equivalent of associate professor) at INAF - Trieste. Since 2021, he is an associate professor of the Physics Department of the University of Trieste.</description></item><item><title>Stefano Cozzini</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/stefano-cozzini/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:49:24 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/stefano-cozzini/</guid><description>Dr. Cozzini is presently the director of the Institute of Research and Technology (RET) at Area Science Park where he is managing all the scientific infrastructures of the campus, including a NGS platform and the ORFEO HPC/AI data center. He teaches HPC topics at DSSC and MHPC and is currently involved in several National and European projects on the above topic. His present scientific interest are in the area between HPC and AI and on FAIR data management.</description></item><item><title>Antonio Celani</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/antonio-celani/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:49:16 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/antonio-celani/</guid><description>Antonio Celani earned his PhD at Politecnico di Torino, Italy in 1998. After post-doctoral fellowships at Max Planck Institute in Munich and at the Observatoire de la Côte d&amp;rsquo;Azur he became researcher for the French National Research Council (CNRS) in 2000. In 2007 he joined the Institut Pasteur Paris as a research director where he started working at the interface between physics and biology. Since 2014 he also is research scientist at The Abdus Salam International Center for Theoretical Physics - ICTP where he works on subjects at the crossroads between physics, biology, and artificial intelligence.</description></item><item><title>Andrea De Lorenzo</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/andrea-de-lorenzo/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:40:35 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/andrea-de-lorenzo/</guid><description>Andrea De Lorenzo is assistant professor at the University of Trieste. His research interests include evolutionary computation, application of machine learning techniques to engineering, computer security problems, information extraction and natural language processing.
He won the silver medal at the 13th Human-Competitive Awards, 2016, for Human-Competitive Results produced by Genetic and Evolutionary Computation. He serves as reviewers for many international journals closely related to his research interests; he is a member of the scientific/program committee of the most important conferences on evolutionary computation.</description></item><item><title>Francesco Pauli</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/francesco-pauli/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:37:44 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/francesco-pauli/</guid><description>Felice Andrea Pellegrino is Associate Professor of Automatica at the Department of Engineering and Architecture, University of Trieste, where he teaches Control Theory and Computer Vision. He has been Research Fellow at SISSA and University of Udine. He is Associate Editor of the IEEE Control Systems Letters and member of the Conference Editorial Boards of the IEEE Control Systems Society and of the European Control Association. His research interests include Control Theory, Machine Learning and Computer Vision.</description></item><item><title>Alberto D'Onofrio</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/alberto-d-onofrio/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:35:52 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/alberto-d-onofrio/</guid><description>Dr d’Onofrio works at the interface between Informatics, Physics and Applied Mathematics. He graduated in Electrical Engineering at Pisa University (1993), and got a PhD in ‘Medical Computer Sciences’ at the Roma Sapienza University (2000). He has been PostDoc, Researcher (2003) and Group Leader (2008) at the European Institute of Oncology, Milan. Between 2014 and 2020 he was Directeur de Recherche at the International Prevention Research Institute, Lyon. Since 2022 he is a Senior Researcher in Computer Science at the Trieste University.</description></item><item><title>Eric Medvet</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/eric-medvet/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:25:31 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/eric-medvet/</guid><description>Eric Medvet is an Associate Professor in Computer Engineering at the Department of Engineering and Architecture of University of Trieste, Italy. He founded and leads the Evolutionary Robotics and Artificial Life lab (ERALlab); he is the co-founder and co-head of the Machine Learning Lab. His research activities include evolutionary computation, artificial life, embodied intelligence, and machine learning applications. He is a member of the program committee of the most important conferences on evolutionary computation.</description></item><item><title>Sara Marceglia</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/sara-marceglia/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:25:24 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/sara-marceglia/</guid><description>Sara Marceglia is Professor of eHealth at the University of Trieste. Her research interests regard the development of personalized applications, decision support systems, and telemedicine systems for fragile patients, with particular attention to neurologic patients. She works to implement integrated systems for chronic patients’ management, including cloud-based data collection platforms, big data analytics infrastructures, ecosystems of personalized app for Patient Reported Outcome collection, and wearable non-stigmatizing telemonitoring devices. She graduated in Biomedical Engineering at (2004) and got her PhD in Bioengineering (2009) at the Politecnico di Milano.</description></item><item><title>Luca Manzoni</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/luca-manzoni/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:23:12 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/luca-manzoni/</guid><description>Luca Manzoni is an assistant professor (associate professor from July 2022) in the field of Evolutionary Computation, Artificial Intelligence, and Natural Computing. He received multiple awards for his research work, he is currently an associate editor of Swarm and Evolutionary Computation. In the last five years he held courses from the bachelor to the PhD level on the topics of algorithms, computational complexity, computer architectures, operating systems, information retrieval, and evolutionary computation.</description></item><item><title>Leonardo Egidi</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/leonardo-egidi/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:22:02 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/leonardo-egidi/</guid><description>Dr Egidi graduated in Statistics from the University of Trieste (2011 and 2014), and obtained a PhD in Statistics from the University of Padova (2018). Since 2020 he is an Assistant Professor of Statistics at the University of Trieste. He regularly teaches Bayesian inference and statistical methods, and is interested in computational statistics and its applications to biostatistics, social sciences and sport analytics. Dr Egidi is a fellow of the Italian Statistical Society and the International Society for Bayesian Analysis.</description></item><item><title>Domenico De Stefano</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/domenico-de-stefano/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:15:59 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/domenico-de-stefano/</guid><description>Domenico De Stefano obtained his PhD in Statistics from the University of Naples Federico II in 2009. Since 2020, he is Full Professor of Social Statistics at the University of Trieste. His teaching activities are in the field of statistics, survey methods and network analysis. His research interests mainly focus on social network analysis and statistical modelling, with particular attention to the development of new methodological tools to explore relational data.</description></item><item><title>Daniele Coslovich</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/daniele-coslovich/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:14:27 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/daniele-coslovich/</guid><description>Prof. Coslovich is Associate Professor at the Physics Department of the University of Trieste since 2020. Previously, he worked at the University of Montpellier and at the Technical University of Vienna. His research interests focus on the theoretical and computational modelling of disordered systems and soft materials. He also contributes to several open source packages for molecular simulations and data analysis.</description></item><item><title>Lorenzo Castelli</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/lorenzo-castelli/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 16:12:43 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/lorenzo-castelli/</guid><description>Prof. Lorenzo Castelli graduated in Electronic Engineering (1997) from the University of Trieste and holds a PhD in Transportation (2002) from the same university. Since 2019 he’s associate professor in Operations Research. His research activity focusses on productivity analysis and mathematical optimisation applied to logistics and transport, with emphasis on various aspects of air traffic management, including market-based mechanisms for slot allocation and pricing mechanisms to redistribute traffic across the European air network.</description></item><item><title>Luca Bortolussi</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/luca-bortolussi/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 15:47:43 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/luca-bortolussi/</guid><description>Luca Bortolussi is full professor of computer science at the University of Trieste. He obtained a phd in computer science from the university of Udine in 2007, and after that worked in Trieste, with periods spent in the School of Informatics of the University of Edinburgh and in the Faculty of Informatics of Saarland University in Saarbruecken. His research interests cover machine learning and artificial intelligence, including explainable AI integrating symbolic and statistic methods, robust machine learning, data generation, stochastic simulation, control and reinforcement learning, with application to complex systems, cyber-physical systems and medicine.</description></item><item><title>Giulia Bernardini</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/giulia-bernardini/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 15:46:23 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/giulia-bernardini/</guid><description>Dr. Bernardini received her M.Sc. in Mathematics from the University of Pisa in 2017, and obtained a Ph.D. in Computer Science from the University of Milano-Bicocca in 2021, winning the Best Italian Ph.D. Thesis in Theoretical Computer Science prize, awarded by the Italian Chapter of EATCS. She spent one year as a Postdoc researcher at the Centrum Wiskunde en Informatica in Amsterdam, and she is an Assistant Professor at the University of Trieste since January 2022.</description></item><item><title>Marco Barchiesi</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/marco-barchiesi/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 May 2022 15:44:53 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/marco-barchiesi/</guid><description>Since October 2019, I am associate professor of probability at the Department of Mathematics and Geosciences of the University of Trieste. I spent most of my career, from October 2010 to September 2019, at the University of Naples Federico II, first as ERC postdoc, then as assistant professor, and finally as associate professor in mathematical analysis. Before that, I was postdoc at the Basque Center for Applied Mathematics and at the Center for Nonlinear Analysis, Carnegie Mellon University.</description></item><item><title>Giovanni Baj</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/giovanni-baj/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 19:02:41 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/giovanni-baj/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Sylvio Barbon Jr</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/sylvio-barbon-jr/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 19:02:13 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/sylvio-barbon-jr/</guid><description>Sylvio is an Associate Professor at the Department of Engineering and Architecture at the University of Trieste (UNITS) and part of the Machine Learning Lab. Previously, he was the leader of the research group that studies machine learning at the State University of Londrina (UEL), Brazil. He received his BSc degree in Computer Science in 2005, MSc degree in Computational Physics from the University of São Paulo (2007), a degree in Computational Engineering in 2008, and PhD degree (2011) from IFSC/USP.</description></item><item><title>Giulia Barbati</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/giulia-barbati/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 18:59:47 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/giulia-barbati/</guid><description>G. Barbati graduated in Statistics from University of Rome (1999) and obtained a PhD in Functional Neuroimaging from University of Chieti-Pescara (2007). Since 2019, she is Associate Professor in Medical Statistics at University of Trieste. She works on survival analysis methods and joint models for longitudinal and time-to-event data. Moreover, she is interested in statistical methods for exploiting informational content of health administrative data and in machine learning (ML) algorithms for risk prediction.</description></item><item><title>Alice Antonello</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/alice-antonello/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 15:26:42 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/students/alice-antonello/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Simone Arnaldi</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/simone-arnaldi/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2022 14:45:44 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/simone-arnaldi/</guid><description>Simone Arnaldi graduated in International relations and diplomacy (2000) from the University of Trieste, and obtained a PhD from the Pontifical Gregorian University (2005). He is Associate Professor of Sociology at the University of Trieste. He studies the governance of science, technology, and innovation (STI) governance, with a focus on responsibility in STI and on science diplomacy. He is the President of the Italian Society of Science and Technology Studies (STS Italia).</description></item><item><title>Giulio Caravagna</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/giulio-caravagna/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 15:44:26 +0200</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/people/faculty/giulio-caravagna/</guid><description>Since 2020, Giulio leads the Cancer Data Science Laboratory at the University of Trieste, a group of interdisciplinary scientists working at the intersection of computational and experimental research, approaching real-world biological questions with state-of-the-art Machine Learning. Giulio trained in computer science at the University of Pisa; after a PhD (2011), he carried out postdoctoral training in mathematical models for biology at Milan-Bicocca, in machine learning for biology at the University of Edinburgh , and in evolutionary cancer genomics at the Institute of Cancer Research.</description></item><item><title>Advanced topics in network analysis: theory and applications</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/advanced-topics-in-network-analysis-theory-and-applications/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/advanced-topics-in-network-analysis-theory-and-applications/</guid><description>Network analysis is a set of statistical techniques focused on uncovering and modeling patterns of relationships that arise from the interactions of people, groups, organizations, or any other entities. Network analysis is an in-demand approach to data analysis because it identifies underlying structures within data characterized by complex dependence structures. This short course will examine the most recent developments in statistical methods for analyzing and modeling the structure and dynamics of complex networks.</description></item><item><title>Advanced topics in Reinforcement Learning</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/advanced-topics-in-reinforcement-learning/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/advanced-topics-in-reinforcement-learning/</guid><description>This short course will address issues in Multi-agent reinforcement learning, from Markov games and the connection with game theory to multi-armed bandit algorithms.</description></item><item><title>Advanced topics in statistical modeling</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/artificial-intelligence-in-society/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/artificial-intelligence-in-society/</guid><description>The course extends basic statistical models through the introduction of multilevel/ hierarchical models, semi and non-parametric regression models, spline functions, penalized likelihood approaches (such as LASSO and Ridge regression models), and hierarchical models for estimating smooth regression functions. Applications to complex datasets and simulation approaches will be illustrated during the course through the use of the Stan ecosystem and the statistical software R.</description></item><item><title>Apply to ADSAI</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/how-to-apply/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/how-to-apply/</guid><description>Admission procedure 2022 application deadline: to be announced soon.
Eligibility The 2022 call is opened to applicants with any 2nd degree title to be held by October 2022. Each applicant should provide:
curriculum vitae et studiorum (free format, reporting exams and marks); final thesis/project abstract; (optional) up to two letters of reference. Reference letters (english, letter-headed paper) are highly suggested, but not compulsory.
The admission paperwork is managed centrally by the University of Trieste, and general instructions to apply can be found at this webpage.</description></item><item><title>Artificial Intelligence in society</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/advanced-topics-in-statistical-modeling/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/advanced-topics-in-statistical-modeling/</guid><description>Artificial intelligence (AI) holds the promise of advancing society in a number of ways. At the same time, AI is increasingly implicated in controversies around its applications. Such an ambivalent public image of AI has led scientific societies, firms, governments and regulators to become more active in issuing blueprints, strategies, and regulations aimed at steering AI towards desirable social goals, while averting negative impacts on society. The Module will discuss the societal implications of AI, by reviewing the social and ethical aspects of this field and by fostering students&amp;rsquo; imagination and reflection on possible ways to make concrete R&amp;amp;I processes more socially responsible.</description></item><item><title>Biodiversity Informatics</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/biodiversity-informatics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/biodiversity-informatics/</guid><description>The course aims at providing basic knowledge to organize, manage, and use biodiversity databases, both at management and research level. Furthermore, it aims at providing knowledge to support students in the drafting of research projects and proposals. Specifically, the course will provide: knowledge of the different types of data that exist in the field of biodiversity; understanding of the modern approached form digitizing, aggregating, and managing different types of biodiversity data; understanding of species distribution models; knowledge of the main tools for the production of interactive digital identification keys, and understanding of their logic.</description></item><item><title>Copula modeling – Extreme value theory</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/copula-modelingextreme-value-theory/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/copula-modelingextreme-value-theory/</guid><description>The course will give a brief introduction to univariate methods for extreme value modeling (generalized Pareto distribution, Poisson point process) with and without covariates. The course will offer a basic introduction to copulas for dependence modelling and their main properties, along with the most important theoretical results. Applications to relevant fields will be illustrated: computation of Value at Risk in finance; Risk Aggregation; Financial time series modelling with copulas.</description></item><item><title>Courses</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/</guid><description>The ADSAI PhD program offers different types of training courses, some of them offered in collaboration with the Theoretical and Scientific Data Science (TSDS) PhD program at SISSA, as well as with the Master in Data Science and Scientific Computing (DSSC) at the University of Trieste.
Following regulations regarding the university educational credits (CFU) system, every year ADSAI students need to define a training program in collaboration wiht their superviors; the program can involve ADSAI courses, partner courses and attendance to conferences/ schools.</description></item><item><title>Curricula at ADSAI</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/curricula/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/curricula/</guid><description>The ADSAI faculty and students are divided into three curricula:
Industry and natural sciences, coordinated by Prof. Luca Bortolussi; Life sciences and medicine, coordinated by Prof. Giulia Barbati; Economy and society, coordinated by Prof. Domenica De Stefano.</description></item><item><title>Economy and society at ADSAI</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/curricula_eco/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/curricula_eco/</guid><description>Synopsis Background &amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;.
Motivation &amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;.
ADSAI ambition &amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;.
Expected outcome &amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;.
Governance Coordinator: Prof xxxx
Prof xxxx (xxxx@units.it), Department of xxxx Simone Arnaldi Leonardo Egidi Luca Manzoni Francesco Pauli Nicola Torelli</description></item><item><title>Evolutionary Robotics</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/explainable-ai/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/explainable-ai/</guid><description>The course introduces the main concepts of evolutionary robotics, that is, the family of optimization techniques based on the paradigm of natural evolution (evolutionary computation) and the principle of embodied cognition. Moreover, it surveys recent and significant research works on evolutionary robotics, highlighting their methodological aspects and their potential applicability to other domains. Concerning evolutionary computation, beyond key components, the course covers its application to the optimization of neural networks. Finally, the course introduces the reality gap problem and briefly surveys the main mitigation strategies.</description></item><item><title>Explainable AI</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/evolutionary-robotics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/evolutionary-robotics/</guid><description>The course on explainable artificial intelligence deals with the hot topic of identifying either efficient models that are also human comprehensible or to build explanations from highly efficient but black-box deep learning models. We will describe from a high level perspective the different approaches for deep learning models (e.g. local and global approximations/distillations and feature ranking) and also introduce some ideas from neuro-symbolic computing, attempting to combine logic and deep learning.</description></item><item><title>Faculty</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/_faculty/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/_faculty/</guid><description>ADSAI Program Director Prof. Francesco Pauli, Department of Economics, Business, Mathematics and Statistics (DEAMS), University of Trieste.
Contacts: dottorato.adsai@units.it.
ADSAI core members Core members are potential supervisors for ADSAI PhD students, are involved in teaching and training and are responsible for the governance of the ADSAI PhD program.
University of Trieste faculties Email Brief biography Research Interests Laboratory Simone Arnaldi sarnaldi@units.it Simone Arnaldi graduated in International relations and diplomacy (2000) from the University of Trieste, and obtained a PhD from the Pontifical Gregorian University (2005).</description></item><item><title>Frequently Asked Questions (FAQs)</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/faq/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/faq/</guid><description>The FAQs are intended for both students and potential sponsors of ADSAI fellowships.
For any question not already covered in thes FAQs, please contact the ADSAI PhD coordinator.
Governance What is the official ADSAI teaching language?
All of ADSAI teaching is in English.
What is the official ADSAI teaching language?
All of ADSAI teaching is in English.
Is ADSAI part of the National PhD program in AI?</description></item><item><title>Home</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/home/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/home/</guid><description>Mission Across all fields, technological development is fostering the collection of large amounts of complex datasets that require advanced data science skills to be organised, processed and successfully mined. Without novel machine learning methods able to interpret and extract knowledge from those datasets, our capacity to understand the world is severely limited. Data Science and Artificial Intelligence are two cross-disciplinary fields rooted at the grounds of computer science, mathematics, statistics and physics to advance our ability to understand complex phenomena through the use of massive data.</description></item><item><title>Industry and natural sciences at ADSAI</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/curricula_ind/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/curricula_ind/</guid><description>Synopsis Background &amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;.
Motivation &amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;.
ADSAI ambition &amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;.
Expected outcome &amp;hellip;&amp;hellip;.
Governance Coordinator: Prof Luca Bortolussi.
Prof Luca Bortolussi (lbortolussi@units.it), Department of Mathematics and Geosciences Prof Marco Barchiesi (mbarchiesi@units.it), Department of Mathematics and Geosciences Prof Daniele Coslovich (dcoslovich@units.it), Department of Physics Dr Stefano Cozzini (stefano.cozzini@areasciencepark.it), Area Science Park Prof Eric Medvet (emedvet@units.it), Department of Engineering and Architecture Prof Felice Andrea Pellegrino (fapellegrino@units.</description></item><item><title>Law and AI</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/law-and-ai/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/law-and-ai/</guid><description>The course on ‘Law and AI’ focuses on how current and prospective legal rules constrain and govern data science and AI applications, especially in the European legal framework. The course will explore the general legal requirements currently applicable to data science and AI applications in Europe, as well as the ongoing debate on prospective legal measures that could in the future apply in the field. Through the analysis of regulatory texts and proposals, judicial decisions and scholarly studies, the course will in particular delve into the protection of privacy, obligations of transparency and fairness, and accountability rules.</description></item><item><title>Life Sciences and medicine at ADSAI</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/curricula_ls/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/curricula_ls/</guid><description>Synopsis Background Life Science, broadly including Medicine and Healthcare, are disciplines that drive conception and development of technologies that, over the last decades, have been impacting society the most. Innovation in these sectors stems from the need to deeply comprehend complex biological phenomena, characterise their fundamental mechanisms and pathological states, learn the effect of our therapeutical interventions onto them and, eventually, enhance our ability to predict human trajectories in both natural and diseases states.</description></item><item><title>MISSION</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/mission/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/mission/</guid><description>Mission Across all fields, technological development is fostering the collection of large amounts of complex datasets that require advanced data science skills to be organised, processed and successfully mined. Without novel machine learning methods able to interpret and extract knowledge from those datasets, our capacity to understand the world is severely limited. Data Science and Artificial Intelligence are two cross-disciplinary fields rooted at the grounds of computer science, mathematics, statistics and physics to advance our ability to understand complex phenomena through the use of massive data.</description></item><item><title>Optimization-based control</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/optimization-based-control/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/optimization-based-control/</guid><description>The course on &amp;lsquo;Optimization-based control&amp;rsquo; will deal with optimization applied to control of linear, possibly constrained, discrete-time dynamical systems. After an introduction to the linear discrete-time dynamical systems and a survey of the relevant basic results of systems theory, the focus will be on (i) How to employ optimization to get open-loop optimal control sequences,(ii) How to get closed-loop control laws from open-loop control sequences, (iii) How to employ online optimization to control dynamical systems; (iv) How to employ optimization to get open-loop optimal control sequences in a model-free, data-driven fashion.</description></item><item><title>People</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/_people/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/_people/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Population-based Optimisation Methods</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/population-based-optimisation-methods/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/population-based-optimisation-methods/</guid><description>The course &amp;ldquo;Population-based Optimization Methods&amp;rdquo; focuses on a collection of methods, generally inspired by natural phenomena, used for optimization and where multiple solutions to the same problems are iteratively improved. In this course we will explore genetic algorithms, genetic programming, evolution strategies, particle swarm optimization, differential evolution, how to represent particular problem domains (e.g., graphs and permutations), neuroevolution, common parallelization techniques, and a brief introduction to the runtime analysis of bio-inspired algorithms.</description></item><item><title>Review of statistical modeling and inference</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/review-of-statistical-modeling-and-inference/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/review-of-statistical-modeling-and-inference/</guid><description>The course is aimed at reviewing the fundamentals of statistical theory within the classical statistical paradigm. We review the whole setting of likelihood theory, with a special focus on maximum likelihood estimation, properties of maximum likelihood estimators and a brief review of hypothesis testing. We deepen then linear and generalized linear models, covering the basic theory of these modeling techniques, the main inferential tools and proposing applications with real and complex data.</description></item><item><title>Statistical methods for clinical prediction models and causal inference</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/statistical-methods-for-clinical-prediction-models-and-causal-inference-an-introduction/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/courses/statistical-methods-for-clinical-prediction-models-and-causal-inference-an-introduction/</guid><description>In this course, we will briefly introduce the principal study designs in epidemiology and clinical research. Then, according to the objectives of the study, we will describe the statistical approaches underlying the two main aims in health research, i.e. predicting prognosis and estimating the causal effect of specific exposures on the outcomes. In the first case the focus will be on describing the main steps involved in building a reliable prediction model (from the selection of covariates to the internal and external validation).</description></item><item><title>Students</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/_students/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/_students/</guid><description>2021 Cohort Student Email Bachelor of Science Master of Science ADSAI supervisor(s) External supervisors Topic Alice Antonello alice.antonello@phd.units.it Biotechnology (University of Turin) Quantitative and Computational Biology (University of Trento) Giulio Caravagna Computational methods for tumor evolution Giovanni Baj giovanni.baj@phd.units.it Physics (University of Insubria) Physics (University of Insubria) Giulia Barbati Arjuna Scagnetto (ASUGI) Applications of AI in Health Care Lorenzo Basile lorenzo.</description></item><item><title>The ADSAI PhD program</title><link>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/phd-program/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.inginf.units.it/phd-program/</guid><description>“Artificial Intelligence is the new electricity.” Andrew Ng, Co-founder and lead of Google Brain.
The Applied Data Science and Artificial Intelligence (ADSAI) PhD program at the Univeristy of Trieste started with the 2021 cohort, and since 2021 ADSAI is also part of the Italian National PhD program in Artificial Intelligence.
Frequenty Asked Questions (FAQ). Contact: phd.adsai@units.it Motivation and objectives Why a PhD in applied Data Science and Artificial Intelligence?</description></item></channel></rss>