<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Courses on Applied Data Science &amp; Artificial Intelligence</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/courses/</link><description>Recent content in Courses on Applied Data Science &amp; Artificial Intelligence</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><atom:link href="https://adsai.units.it/courses/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Advanced topics in network analysis: theory and applications</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/courses/advanced-topics-in-network-analysis-theory-and-applications/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.units.it/courses/advanced-topics-in-network-analysis-theory-and-applications/</guid><description>Network analysis is a set of statistical techniques focused on uncovering and modeling patterns of relationships that arise from the interactions of people, groups, organizations, or any other entities. Network analysis is an in-demand approach to data analysis because it identifies underlying structures within data characterized by complex dependence structures. This short course will examine the most recent developments in statistical methods for analyzing and modeling the structure and dynamics of complex networks.</description></item><item><title>Advanced topics in Reinforcement Learning</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/courses/advanced-topics-in-reinforcement-learning/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.units.it/courses/advanced-topics-in-reinforcement-learning/</guid><description>This short course will address issues in Multi-agent reinforcement learning, from Markov games and the connection with game theory to multi-armed bandit algorithms.</description></item><item><title>Advanced topics in statistical modeling</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/courses/artificial-intelligence-in-society/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.units.it/courses/artificial-intelligence-in-society/</guid><description>The course extends basic statistical models through the introduction of multilevel/ hierarchical models, semi and non-parametric regression models, spline functions, penalized likelihood approaches (such as LASSO and Ridge regression models), and hierarchical models for estimating smooth regression functions. Applications to complex datasets and simulation approaches will be illustrated during the course through the use of the Stan ecosystem and the statistical software R.</description></item><item><title>Artificial Intelligence in society</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/courses/advanced-topics-in-statistical-modeling/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.units.it/courses/advanced-topics-in-statistical-modeling/</guid><description>Artificial intelligence (AI) holds the promise of advancing society in a number of ways. At the same time, AI is increasingly implicated in controversies around its applications. Such an ambivalent public image of AI has led scientific societies, firms, governments and regulators to become more active in issuing blueprints, strategies, and regulations aimed at steering AI towards desirable social goals, while averting negative impacts on society.</description></item><item><title>Biodiversity Informatics</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/courses/biodiversity-informatics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.units.it/courses/biodiversity-informatics/</guid><description>The course aims at providing basic knowledge to organize, manage, and use biodiversity databases, both at management and research level. Furthermore, it aims at providing knowledge to support students in the drafting of research projects and proposals. Specifically, the course will provide: knowledge of the different types of data that exist in the field of biodiversity; understanding of the modern approached form digitizing, aggregating, and managing different types of biodiversity data; understanding of species distribution models; knowledge of the main tools for the production of interactive digital identification keys, and understanding of their logic.</description></item><item><title>Copula modeling – Extreme value theory</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/courses/copula-modelingextreme-value-theory/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.units.it/courses/copula-modelingextreme-value-theory/</guid><description>The course will give a brief introduction to univariate methods for extreme value modeling (generalized Pareto distribution, Poisson point process) with and without covariates. The course will offer a basic introduction to copulas for dependence modelling and their main properties, along with the most important theoretical results. Applications to relevant fields will be illustrated: computation of Value at Risk in finance; Risk Aggregation; Financial time series modelling with copulas.</description></item><item><title>Evolutionary Robotics</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/courses/explainable-ai/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.units.it/courses/explainable-ai/</guid><description>The course introduces the main concepts of evolutionary robotics, that is, the family of optimization techniques based on the paradigm of natural evolution (evolutionary computation) and the principle of embodied cognition. Moreover, it surveys recent and significant research works on evolutionary robotics, highlighting their methodological aspects and their potential applicability to other domains.</description></item><item><title>Explainable AI</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/courses/evolutionary-robotics/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.units.it/courses/evolutionary-robotics/</guid><description>The course on explainable artificial intelligence deals with the hot topic of identifying either efficient models that are also human comprehensible or to build explanations from highly efficient but black-box deep learning models. We will describe from a high level perspective the different approaches for deep learning models (e.g. local and global approximations/distillations and feature ranking) and also introduce some ideas from neuro-symbolic computing, attempting to combine logic and deep learning.</description></item><item><title>Law and AI</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/courses/law-and-ai/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.units.it/courses/law-and-ai/</guid><description>The course on ‘Law and AI’ focuses on how current and prospective legal rules constrain and govern data science and AI applications, especially in the European legal framework. The course will explore the general legal requirements currently applicable to data science and AI applications in Europe, as well as the ongoing debate on prospective legal measures that could in the future apply in the field.</description></item><item><title>Optimization-based control</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/courses/optimization-based-control/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.units.it/courses/optimization-based-control/</guid><description>The course on &amp;lsquo;Optimization-based control&amp;rsquo; will deal with optimization applied to control of linear, possibly constrained, discrete-time dynamical systems. After an introduction to the linear discrete-time dynamical systems and a survey of the relevant basic results of systems theory, the focus will be on (i) How to employ optimization to get open-loop optimal control sequences,(ii) How to get closed-loop control laws from open-loop control sequences, (iii) How to employ online optimization to control dynamical systems; (iv) How to employ optimization to get open-loop optimal control sequences in a model-free, data-driven fashion.</description></item><item><title>Population-based Optimisation Methods</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/courses/population-based-optimisation-methods/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.units.it/courses/population-based-optimisation-methods/</guid><description>The course &amp;ldquo;Population-based Optimization Methods&amp;rdquo; focuses on a collection of methods, generally inspired by natural phenomena, used for optimization and where multiple solutions to the same problems are iteratively improved. In this course we will explore genetic algorithms, genetic programming, evolution strategies, particle swarm optimization, differential evolution, how to represent particular problem domains (e.</description></item><item><title>Review of statistical modeling and inference</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/courses/review-of-statistical-modeling-and-inference/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.units.it/courses/review-of-statistical-modeling-and-inference/</guid><description>The course is aimed at reviewing the fundamentals of statistical theory within the classical statistical paradigm. We review the whole setting of likelihood theory, with a special focus on maximum likelihood estimation, properties of maximum likelihood estimators and a brief review of hypothesis testing. We deepen then linear and generalized linear models, covering the basic theory of these modeling techniques, the main inferential tools and proposing applications with real and complex data.</description></item><item><title>Statistical methods for clinical prediction models and causal inference</title><link>https://adsai.units.it/courses/statistical-methods-for-clinical-prediction-models-and-causal-inference-an-introduction/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://adsai.units.it/courses/statistical-methods-for-clinical-prediction-models-and-causal-inference-an-introduction/</guid><description>In this course, we will briefly introduce the principal study designs in epidemiology and clinical research. Then, according to the objectives of the study, we will describe the statistical approaches underlying the two main aims in health research, i.e. predicting prognosis and estimating the causal effect of specific exposures on the outcomes.</description></item></channel></rss>